Finding Aid for Thomas A. Butts papers, 1961-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Loans
  - Overview
    - Published Information for Students and Institutions 1976-1980 (Box 6)
    - Articles on Loan Programs 1994-1999 (Box 6)
    - Student Interest Rates 1998-2003 (Box 6)
    - "Congressman Wolpe on Nightline," 1992 and "The Future of Student Financial Aid," 1995 (Box 6)
      (VHS Tapes)
  - Papers
    "Papers" subseries (0.5 linear feet, 1977-1986, and 1993-2000) are analyses of student loan issues or programs. Several of the papers evaluate the entire federal financial aid system or the campus based funding system, and offer recommendations for new ones. Also of note is a paper covering the history of student aid programs, from the 1970s through the 1990s.
    - Author Assignments for Student Aid Issue Papers 1978 (Box 6)
    - Basic Education Opportunity Grant (BEOG) Legislation 1977 (Box 6)
    - Campus Based Funding Process, Background and Evaluation 1978 (Box 6)
    - Campus Based Funding Process, Questions and Comments from Nation-wide Hearings 1978 (Box 6)
    - Campus Based Funding Process, Testimony on the Revised Funding Process 1980 (Box 6)
    - Critique of the Roth Amendment and Alternatives to it 1977 (Box 6)
    - Designing a New Funding Process, Meetings and Recommendations of the Panel of Experts 1978 (Box 6)
    - Designing a New Funding Process, Final Report of the Panel of Experts 1979 (Box 6)
    - Enrollment Trends for Michigan Higher Education 1964-1978 (Box 6)
    - Evaluating the Federal Loan System 1978-1979 (Box 6)
    - Federal Family Education Loan Program (FFELP) 1999 (Box 6)
    - Federal Government Loan Policy in the 1990s, 1999-2000 (Box 6)
    - History of Student Aid Programs from the 1970s to the 1990s, 1986, 2000 (Box 6)
    - Loan Consolidation 1981-1983, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Middle Income Squeeze and the Tuition Tax Credit Solution 1977 (Box 6)
    - Recommendations for Improved Management of the Federal Student Aid Programs by the Student Financial Assistance Study Group 1977 (Box 6)
    - The Characteristics of Stafford Student Loan Borrowers in Repayment and the Impact of Educational Debt on Personal and Economic Life Decisions 1993 (Box 6)
    - Supplementary Education Opportunity Grant (SEOG) 1985 (Box 6)
    - The Voyager Loan Program 2000 (Box 6)
  - Memos
    "Memos" subseries (0.25 linear feet, 1980-1981, 1999) are discussions of issues related to specific student loan programs. They were originally housed in a binder together by Thomas Butts, and the original order has been maintained.
    - Education Amendments of 1980 How to Implement the Changes, Effects on the Guaranteed Student Loan Program, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Federal Insured Student Loan Program (FISLP), Lender Contract and Default Claims 1980-1981 (Box 6)
    - Guaranteed Student Loan Program, Refund Regulations, Deferment Regulations, and Need Analysis Formula 1980 (Box 6)
    - Pell Grant Program, FY 1979-1981 (Box 6)
    - Higher Education Act, General Provisions, Title IV 1980 (Box 6)
    - State Student Incentive Grant Program (SSIG) Regulations 1980 (Box 6)
    - Work Incentives Improvement Act: Federal Subsidies 1999 (Box 6)
  - Statistics
    "Statistics" subseries (0.25 linear feet, 1978-1984) provides tables of information on the allocation of funding and default rates by state, institution type, and sometimes by institution. The programs include campus based programs generally, the national direct student loan program, and the Student Education Opportunity Grant (SEOG).
    - Allocation of Funding to Loan Programs 1978-1980 (Box 6)
    - Default Rates, Demographics, and Enrollment of BEOG and SEOG Programs, by State 1978 (Box 6)
    - National Direct Student Loan Default Rate 1979-1980 (Box 6)
    - Comparison of Allocations for Campus Based Programs by State 1979-1981 (Box 6)
    - SEOG Allocation as a Percent of Total Allocation 1980 (Box 7)
    - Change in SEOG Allocation 1984 (Box 7)
  - Higher Education Act
    "Higher Education Act" subseries (1.5 linear feet, 1972-2000) is divided into three sections. "Budget" (0.5 linear feet) covers negotiating and allocating the budget for financial aid programs from 1972 to 1988 and 2000. "Title IV" (0.25 linear feet) is from 1976 to 1977 and 2000. The 1976-1977 materials are hand-written notes covering forming ideas, drafting, and revising, and amending the law. The 2000 material is from negotiated rulemaking sessions on loan issues and program and flexibility issues. "Reauthorization" (0.75 linear feet) covers the reauthorization process for 1980, 1986, and 1992. These mostly consist of testimony before Congressional subcommittees regarding various aspects of the proposed reauthorization. They also include reports and studies on loan options, and correspondence from members of the financial aid community voicing their opinions and concerns. 1986 Reauthorization Correspondence to Congressmen includes many letters to William D. Ford, who would later sponsor the Direct Loan Program. The 1992 Reauthorization, NASULGC meeting includes statements by Congressmen Ford and Anderson.
    - Budget
      - 1972 Budget and Amendments, 1972 (Box 7)
      - Budget Request 1979-1981, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Appropriation Hearings 1981, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Press Releases 1981 (Box 7)
      - President's Budget Reform Plan, Congressional Testimony 1981 (Box 7)
      - Budget Reports and Statistics 1980-1981 (Box 7)
      - Budget Request 1982 (Box 7)
      - 1987, 1988 Budget Needs, 1986-1987 (Box 7)
      - Budget Request 2000 (Box 7)
    - Title IV, Federal Code of Regulations
      - Ideas for Regulations 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Drafting Regulations 1976-1977, 5 folders (Box 7)
      - Regulation Package, Subpart D 1977 (Box 7)
      - Suggested Technical Amendments to the 1976 Law, 1977 (Box 7)
      - Deferment Regulations 1977 (Box 7)
    - Amendment to Title IV to Decrease Fraud 1978 (Box 7)
    - Title IV Negotiated Rulemaking Sessions: Loan Issues 2000 (Box 7)
    - Title IV Negotiated Rulemaking Sessions: Program and Flexibility Issues 2000 (Box 7)
    - 1980 Reauthorization
      - Major Elements of the Reauthorization Proposal 1979 (Box 7)
      - Ford Technical Amendments 1979 (Box 7)
      - Bureau of Student Financial Assistance Position on the Reauthorization Proposals 1978-1979 (Box 8)
      - Review and Analysis 1979-1980 (Box 8)
      - Congressional Testimony
        - American Bankers Association 1979 (Box 8)
        - William Bowen, President of Princeton University 1978 (Box 8)
        - Secretary Joseph A. Califano, Jr. 1978-1979 (Box 8)
        - Members of Congress 1978-1979 (Box 8)
        - Marshall Smith and Tom Butts, Office of Education 1979 (Box 8)
        - United States Student Association and National Council of Higher Education Loan Programs 1979 (Box 8)
        - Several Testimonies from August 1, 1979 (Box 8)
    - 1986 Reauthorization
      - Legislation and Issue Papers 1986 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence 1986 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence with Congressmen 1985-1987 (Box 8)
      - Congressional Testimony
        - People to Testify 1985 (Box 8)
        - Associations for Individual States 1985 (Box 8)
        - Associations for Student Interests 1985 (Box 8)
        - Associations for Universities 1985 (Box 8)
        - Jean Frohlicher, National Council of Higher Education Loan Programs, Inc. 1985 (Box 8)
        - Loan Associations 1985 (Box 8)
        - National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities 1985 (Box 8)
        - National Association of Student Financial Aid Administrators (NASFAA) 1985 (Box 8)
        - National Student Aid Coalition 1985 (Box 8)
        - Non-Profit Student Loan Organizations 1985 (Box 8)
        - Reviews of the Guaranteed Student Loan Program 1985 (Box 8)
    - 1992 Reauthorization
      - Congressman Andrews Direct Student Loan Proposal 1991-1993 (Box 8)
      - NASULGC Student Aid Meeting 1992 (Box 8)
      - Congressional Testimony, Lamar Alexander, U.S. Secretary of Education 1991 (Box 8)
      - American Council of Education, Evaluation of the Loan Programs 1992 (Box 8)
  - Guaranteed Student Loans
    "Guaranteed Student Loans" subseries (0.5 linear feet, 1968-1979 and 1990) is topical files, arranged alphabetically. Of particular note are correspondence from 1978 in which different colleges explain their efforts to ensure access to financial aid for all students, which were sent to Thomas Butts as part of his U.S. Department of Education work, and discussions on how to cope with the problems of the middle income students from 1977 and 1978, called the "Middle Income Squeeze." The other files provide information and statistics on how the program functions, and discussions of other issues pertaining to the program.
    Direct Loan Program" (0.5 linear feet, 1991-2001). Thomas Butts was a strong advocate for the Direct Loan Program. It includes 4 sections. "Memos" (0.2 linear feet) are of different universities and the U.S. Department of Education discussing the Direct Loan Program. "National Direct Student Loan Coalition" includes meeting agendas and records of the executive committee, articles, and Thomas Butts' statement before the Government Reform Subcommittee in 1999. It is a nonprofit corporation founded in 1999. "Program Evaluations" are three analyses of the Direct Loan Program: one of cost, one of the market mechanism, and also a statement of support from University of Michigan President Duderstadt. "Publications" includes two articles, a paper, and a letter to the Washington Post by Thomas Butts, as well as an evaluation of the program by the U.S. Department of Education. The rest of the materials are reports on how the program works and school roster and default rates from 1998.
    - Applying to be a Lender 1969 (Box 8)
    - Assuring Access: Lenders of Last Resort 1978 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence
      - Assurance of Loan Access 1978, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Office of Guaranteed Student Loans 1977-1978 (Box 8)
      - Opinions on the Program 1978-1979 (Box 8)
    - Defaulting on Loans Problem 1978, 1988 (Box 8)
    - Evaluating a Guarantee Agency 1980 (Box 8)
    - Evaluating the Program 1973-1979 (Box 8)
    - Evaluating the Program, Responses to the Fountain Committee 1978 (Box 8)
    - HEAF, the Largest Guarantor of Guaranteed Student Loans, in Financial Trouble 1990 (Box 9)
    - Meeting Notes 1978, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Middle Income Strategy 1977-1978 (Box 9)
    - Middle Income Student Assistance Act 1978 (Box 9)
    - Program Overview 1977 (Box 9)
    - Program Information and Statistics 1968-1990 (Box 9)
    - Proposals for Changes 1977-1978, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Regulations 1978 (Box 9)
    - Statistical Representation of the activities of Guarantee Agencies 1980-1992 (Box 9)
Related Material
Additional information on Thomas Butts is contained in two other collections at the Bentley Historical Library:
University of Michigan Office of Financial Aid
University of Michigan Vice President of Government Relations
List of Common Acronyms
ACRAO -- American Association of Collegiate Registrars and Admission Officers
ACPA -- American College Personnel Association
APDA -- American Professional Development Associates
APGA -- American Personnel and Guidance Association
COSUAA -- Coalition of State University Aid Administrators
HACE -- Higher and Continuing Education
HEEA -- Higher Education Executive Associates
MASFAA -- Midwest Association of Student Financial Aid Administrators
MCPA -- Michigan College Personnel Association
MPGA -- Michigan Personnel and Guidance Association
MSFAA -- Michigan Student Financial Aid Association
NASFAA -- National Association of Student Financial Aid Administrators
NCHELP -- National Council of Higher Education Loan Programs